{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This man was drafted in the 21st round by the Philadelphia Eagles in 1958, but a knee injury ended his playing career a year later. However, during the 1970's, he led the Oakland Raiders to a 76.3% winning percentage in the 142 regular season games he coached. He later was as a commentator for ABC's Monday Night Football. For 10 points, name this former football player, coach, and commentator who is known for endorsing NFL-based video games bearing his name.",
      "answer": "John Madden"
    },
    {
      "question": "The event for which this man is most remembered for occurred on March 2, 1962. During that game, the Knicks deliberately fouled other players to keep the ball away from this man, who at the time played for the Philadelphia Warriors. For 10 points, name this man who holds the NBA record for most points in a regular season with 4,029, and who was the first and only NBA player to score 100 points in a game.",
      "answer": "Wilt Chamberlain"
    },
    {
      "question": "With Douglas Fairbanks, Mary Pickford, and Charlie Chaplin, this man co-founded United Artists. A film by this director was the first film to be shown privately at the White House and was praised by Woodrow Wilson. That film by this director was criticized for its positive portrayal of the Ku Klux Klan. For 10 points, name this director of Birth of a Nation.",
      "answer": "D.W. Griffith"
    },
    {
      "question": "This type of song was repopularized by the Fisk Jubilee Singers. A song of this type written by Charles Wesley says \"My brother, you ought to been there;\" another of these songs repeats \"Tell old Pharaoh, let my people go.\" For 10 points, \"Roll, Jordan, Roll\" and \"Go Down Moses\" are examples of what kind of Christian song often sung by slaves in the antebellum South?",
      "answer": "spirituals NHBB B 2014-2015"
    },
    {
      "question": "As a player, coach, and manager, this man has participated in more World Series than any other man at 21. A famous photo shows him jumping into Don Larsen's arms after having caught Larsen's perfect game for the Yankees during the 1956 World Series. Nowadays, this man is well known for his humorous quotes such as “if you see a fork in the road, take it”. For 10 points, name this longtime New York Yankee catcher whose name was the inspiration for a famous cartoon character.",
      "answer": "Yogi Berra"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man received a gold medal as part of the men's eights team in the 1924 Olympic rowing competition. He later advocated universal health care as the People's Party's candidate in 1972. His published work was so ubiquitous that it was simply called \"the book.\" For 10 points, name this pediatrician who influenced the Baby Boomers with his book Baby and Child Care.",
      "answer": "Dr. Benjamin Spock"
    },
    {
      "question": "A classic simulator of this game included the Lovely Ladies, Ghastly Monsters, and American Dreams as teams. A 2009 simulator of this game contained a notorious error in which awards for the year \"216\" were presented. Early simulators of this game were named for Earl Weaver and Tony La Russa. For 10 points, name this sport played by Barry Bonds and Babe Ruth.",
      "answer": "baseball NHBB B 2014-2015"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these compositions uses words by August Hoffmann and includes a second movement dedicated to wine, women, and song. One of these pieces shares a melody with The Moldau movement of Smetana’s Ma Vlast. Another of these pieces uses the melody “To Anacreon in Heaven” as the setting for a poem commemorating Fort McHenry’s bombardment in the War of 1812 written by Francis Scott Key. For ten points, the Hatikvah, “Deutchlandlied” and “The Star-Spangled Banner” are all what type of song, which is used to represent its country?",
      "answer": "national anthems"
    },
    {
      "question": "This player was selected one pick before David Greenwood after his team won a coin flip against the Chicago Bulls for the number one pick in the 1979 draft. In his final year at Michigan State, he defeated Larry Bird’s Indiana State in the NCAA championship game. This co-owner of the Dodgers started a foundation in 1991 to raise awareness of AIDS after he announced that he was HIV positive. For ten points, name this Hall of Fame point guard for the Los Angeles Lakers.",
      "answer": "Earvin “Magic” Johnson"
    },
    {
      "question": "This artist sang “We met as soulmates on Parris Island” in his song about Vietnam veterans, “Goodnight Saigon.” Another song from his album The Nylon Curtain was inspired by the closing of Bethlehem Steel in Allentown. This Long Island resident rhymed “Bernie Goetz” with “homeless vets” in a song that proclaimed the title phenomenon “was always burning since the world’s been turning.” for ten points, name this singer of “Movin’ Out” and “We Didn’t Start The Fire.”",
      "answer": "Billy Joel"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this film, Brad Kane and Lea Salonga sing a duet that won an Oscar for Best Original Song. After marketing disputes, Dan Castellaneta replaced one voice actor in this film’s first sequel. Thirty percent of respondents to a December 2015 PPP poll supported bombing Agrabah, this movie’s setting, where Jafar seeks a magic lamp. Robin Williams voiced the Genie in, for ten points, what 1992 Disney film adapted from The Arabian Nights?",
      "answer": "Aladdin"
    },
    {
      "question": "This conflict essentially ended after the Battle of Ascalon. During this military campaign, Peter Bartholomew boosted morale when he claimed to have unearthed a relic in the city of Antioch. This campaign was initiated by a speech proclaiming “Deus vult!”, or “God wills it!”, by Urban II. This conflict led to the establishment of kingdoms in Edessa and Jerusalem. For ten points, name this initial medieval campaign to capture the Holy Land.",
      "answer": "First Crusade"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Raiders came back to defeat this team in the 1968 “Heidi” Game, whose ending was cut off on television by a children’s movie. This team won its only Super Bowl by a score of 16 to 7 against Earl Morrall and Johnny Unitas after the quarterback guaranteed an upset victory. Joe Namath is the all-time leading passer for this team, the winner of Super Bowl 3 over the Baltimore Colts. For ten points, name this NFL team that shares the Meadowlands of New Jersey with the New York Giants.",
      "answer": "New York Jets"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1929, Leonard Woolley’s team of archaeologists found four examples of this type of musical instrument in the ruins of Ur. A Samuel Barber Adagio for this type of instruments was JFK’s favorite piece of classical music and was widely broadcast after his assassination. Plectra, picks, or bows may be used to play, for ten points, what class of musical instruments that includes guitars and violins?",
      "answer": [
        "string instruments",
        "lyres and/or harps",
        "Adagio for Strings after “Samuel” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1957, this musician canceled a Soviet Union tour in solidarity with the Little Rock Nine. Kid Ory was part of this musician’s “Hot Five” band, which added Pete Briggs and drummer Al Dodds to become the “Hot Seven” in 1927. This man, the first jazz musician to reach the cover of Time magazine, won a Grammy in 1964 for his performance of “Hello, Dolly!” For ten points, name this legendary jazz trumpeter and singer of “What a Wonderful World,” known as Satchmo.",
      "answer": "Louis Armstrong"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1998, the National Film Registry preserved a film of this event created by camera shop owner Barley Elliot. Gig Harbor was one of the endpoints of the central structure involved in this event, which wasdesignedbyLeonMoisseiff.AdognamedTubbyperishedinthisevent,inwhich40mileanhourwinds caused an irregular torsional vibrational mode that led the central structure to flap. For ten points, name this disaster along a structure nicknamed “Galloping Gertie” crossing the Puget Sound in Washington.",
      "answer": [
        "collapse or failure, etc. of the Tacoma Narrows Bridge",
        "Galloping Gertie in place of Tacoma Narrows Bridge before “Galloping” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "After winning this event in 1987, Harry Carson dumped a bucket of popcorn over President Reagan’s head at the White House. CEO Jed York claimed to have “pulled the plug” on one of these events in 2013, refuting Ray Lewis’ claim that the power outage at the Louisiana Superdome was a conspiracy. For ten points, name this event, annually the most-watched television program in the United States, that determines the champion of the NFL.",
      "answer": [
        "Super Bowl",
        "Super Bowl 21 and/or 47"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The Croatian War began at one of these locations called Maksimir following a fight between a police officer and Zvonimir Boban. One of these places in Croke became the site of an infamous massacre perpetrated by British troops on Bloody Sunday. The Sun newspaper was effectively banned from one city after it erroneously claimed that the Hillsborough disaster at one of these facilities was caused by onrushing Liverpool fans. For ten points, name these places where teams like Arsenal and Manchester United play football.",
      "answer": "soccer stadiums"
    },
    {
      "question": "AfterameetingwithHenryMorgenthau,thismanproducedafilmbasedontheideasofairsuperiority purported by Alexander de Seversky. This man, who hired a writing corps known as the “Nine Old Men,” produced a film that includes a dream sequence set in a Nazi factory and salutes to Hitler. Leopold Stokowski conducted the Philadelphia Orchestra for an animated film by, for ten points, what animator and producer of Der Fuehrer’s Face and Fantasia, which star Donald Duck and Mickey Mouse?",
      "answer": "Walt Disney"
    },
    {
      "question": "Grace Kelly invited this man to Monaco in 1958 to arrange a benefit concert with Frank Sinatra at the Monaco Sporting Club. In 1968, Bob Russell and this man became the first African-Americans to be nominated for an Academy Award for Best Original Song for “The Eyes of Love” from the film Banning. In 1984, this man won the Grammy for Album Of The Year for producing Michael Jackson’s Thriller. For ten points, name this legendary music producer, who holds the record for all-time Grammy nominations.",
      "answer": "Quincy Jones"
    },
    {
      "question": "This team played on Huntington Avenue before moving to its current stadium in 1912 and was a crosstown rival of the Braves until 1952. This team has had three Triple Crown winners, including one player who did it in both 1952 and 1957. In 2005 this team hired baseball’s youngest General Manager, Theo Epstein. For ten points, Steve Pearce, Johnny Damon, and Babe Ruth helped what New York Yankees rival win three of their nine titles, including the first World Series in 1903 when they were simply named “the Americans”?",
      "answer": [
        "Boston Red Sox",
        "either Boston",
        "Red Sox 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 4"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This document warned of unrestricted submarine warfare in the Atlantic Ocean. This message suggested the “immediate adherence” of Japan, and promised its recipient material assistance in recapturing territories lost in an earlier conflict. The intention of this coded message was to occupy the United States in a local conflict and keep it out of the war with Europe. For ten points, name this cable, intercepted in 1917, that contributed to the entry of the United States into World War One.",
      "answer": [
        "Zimmermann Telegram",
        "Zimmermann Note,",
        "Zimmermann Cable before mentioned 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 1"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This figure held 1960s jazz concerts in his backyard, including acts like Dave Brubeck and Dizzy Gillespie, to raise funds for the Southern Christian Leadership Conference. This founder of the Black-owned Freedom National Bank was defended by teammate Pee-Wee Reese by saying \"You can hate a man for many reasons. Color is not one of them.\" The first Black man to break the color barrier in Major League Baseball was, for ten points, which Brooklyn Dodgers baseball player?",
      "answer": "Jackie Robinson or Jack Roosevelt Robinson"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Soviet Union boycotted this event in favor of their own Spartakiad to be hosted in Barcelona the following year. The reporters of Der Stürmer [[SHTIR-muh]] were banned from the host city during this procession. Prior to this event, Adidas founder Adolf Dassler convinced Jesse Owens to wear his shoes prior to the Long Jump competition. For ten points, name this 1936 athletic event hosted by the government of Adolf Hitler in the German capital.",
      "answer": [
        "Berlin Olympics",
        "1936 Olympics before \"1936\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Near the end of this decade, Link Wray released the song “Rumble,” and Alan Freed’s career tanked due to the Payola scandal. Number one hits in this decade included “The Ballad of Davy Crockett,” “Love Me Tender,” and “La Bamba.” At this decade’s end, a plane crash called “The Day the Music Died” resulted in the deaths of Richie Valens, The Big Bopper, and Buddy Holly. For ten points, name this decade in which the rock-and-roll hit \"Heartbreak Hotel\" became a number one hit for Elvis Presley.",
      "answer": "1950s"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this U.S. state, a team of death row inmates played baseball as the \"Alston's All- Stars\" to postpone their own execution date. This state's Fort Laramie served as a staging ground for army offensives during the Great Sioux [[SOOH]] Wars of the 1870s. While a territory, this modern state became the first to allow women to vote in its elections, leading to its nickname, the \"Equality State\". For ten points, name this state that, since 1890, has been governed from Cheyenne.",
      "answer": "Wyoming"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man portrayed a defense attorney in Anatomy of a Murder. This man's roles in No Highway in the Sky and Flight of the Phoenix were inspired by his distinguished service as a pilot in World War II. With a frequent collaborator, he starred in Rear Window and Vertigo. For 10 points, name this star of four Alfred Hitchock films and It's a Wonderful Life.",
        "answer": "James \"Jimmy\" Stewart"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1954, Stewart starred in a biopic about what trombone player and bandleader, who disappeared during World War II after being arguably the most popular musician of the early 40s?",
        "answer": "Glenn Miller"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This current baseball team debuted as the White Stockings in 1870, and adopted its current name in 1907. This team reached the NLCS in 1984 and 1989 under the leadership of Ryne Sandberg, but failed to make the World Series. It is the oldest currently active Major League Baseball team, but the last of its 16 National League pennants came in 1930, and it hasn't won the World Series since 1908. For 10 points, name this Major League Baseball team that plays its games within the ivy-covered friendly confines of Wrigley Field in Chicago.",
        "answer": "Chicago Cubs"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which is the only current Major League baseball stadium that is older than the Cubs’ Wrigley Field?",
        "answer": "Fenway Park"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A comic book series starring this character is where The Punisher first appeared. In the 1970s, this character was tormented by The Jackal creating clones of his loved ones, which provided the basis for a reviled 1990s \"Clone Saga\" storyline. For 10 points, name this Marvel character who opposes Dr. Octopus, The Lizard, and Venom and is the alter-ego of Peter Parker.",
        "answer": "Spider-Man"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which singer, who sang about the Troubles in Northern Ireland in his band’s song Sunday, Bloody Sunday, wrote the music to the ill-fated Broadway musical about Spiderman?",
        "answer": [
          "Bono",
          "Paul Hewson,"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This character's British counterpart was a real person named Ruby Loftus, and her Canadian version was Ronnie the Bren Gun Girl. This character is distinct from the subject of the Howard Miller \"We Can Do It!\" poster, and was popularized by a Norman Rockwell painting. For 10 points, name this World War II poster character who promoted women's working in factories.",
        "answer": "Rosie the Riveter"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "American women also competed in a professional baseball league during the war, which ended up being the subject of what 1990’s film starring Geena Davis and Madonna?",
        "answer": "A League of Their Own"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "William Christopher replaced George Morgan on this show as chaplain Mulcahy. This show had two spinoffs, including the contemporary-set Trapper John, M.D. This TV show was based on a 1970 Robert Altman film, and its 1983 finale remains the highest-rated episode of a scripted TV show ever. For 10 points, name this sitcom set during the Korean War.",
        "answer": "M*A*S*H"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The second-most watched non-sports broadcast in American history was what late 1970s miniseries, based on an Alex Haley novel about his slave ancestors?",
        "answer": "Roots"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city has for decades been the center of the least populated metro area to be the home of a\nmajor American professional sports team. This city’s team is notable for its ownership structure,\nwhich consists of numerous shareholders and a stock sale in 1998 to help renovate its notoriously\ncold stadium at Lambeau (LAM-boe) Field. This city’s team name references an industry that\nwas criticized in Upton Sinclair’s The Jungle. For 10 points, name this Wisconsin city on an arm\nof Lake Michigan, with a highly successful National Football League team.",
        "answer": "Green Bay"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which former Green Bay quarterback had a role in the 1998 Farrelly brothers comedy\nfilm, There’s Something About Mary?",
        "answer": [
          "Brett Favre",
          "Favre"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This song asks \"where is that band who so vaultingly swore\" and observes \"where the foes'\nhaughty host in dread silence reposes\" in its little-heard additional verses. The British bar song\nsong \"To Anacreon in Heaven\" was used to set the lyrics of this song. For 10 points, name this\nsong written during the British bombardment of Fort McHenry by Francis Scott Key.",
        "answer": "The Star-Spangled Banner"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Fort McHenry is found guarding the harbor of what major city?",
        "answer": "Baltimore"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A character in the story of this holiday is described with the mysterious epithet \"the Agagite.\" This holiday's story describes the court of a king often thought to be Xerxes (ZERK-seez), who gets rid of his wife Vashti and marries Esther. For 10 points, identify this Jewish holiday which celebrates deliverance from the Persian vizier Haman in a carnival-like atmosphere.",
        "answer": "Purim"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which style of Jewish music, which often features clarinets and accordions and was influenced by jazz, is sometimes played to celebrate Purim and other Jewish holidays?",
        "answer": "Klezmer"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city sought to demolish the Western Metal Supply Company building, then decided to use it for the left field foul pole in a baseball stadium. This city’s Major League Baseball team lost the 1984 and 1998 World Series, despite the hitting of Tony Gwynn, and its NFL team, led by Philip Rivers, is considering leaving Qualcomm Stadium for Los Angeles in 2016. For ten points, name this Southern California city home to baseball’s Padres and, for possibly not much longer, football’s Chargers.",
        "answer": "San Diego"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This other NFL team, once owned by the late Al Davis, is considering moving back to Los Angeles after two decades and numerous NFL lawsuits in the Bay Area.",
        "answer": [
          "Oakland Raiders",
          "either city",
          "team name"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In one of this director’s films, Colonel Dax defends his troops after they refuse to conduct a suicidal charge on enemy lines during World War I. This director’s collaborations with Kirk Douglas include the aforementioned Paths of Glory, as well as a film following the Roman gladiator, Spartacus. In another of this man’s movies, Peter Sellers plays 3 different roles, including the title handicapped, former-Nazi scientist. For ten points, name this American anti-war director of Dr. Strangelove, as well as 2001: A Space Odyssey.",
        "answer": "Stanley Kubrick"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This other Kubrick war film, which follows a platoon of Marines during the Vietnam War, includes R. Lee Ermey as a diabolical drill sergeant.",
        "answer": "Full Metal Jacket"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A group created to perform this action was founded by Abraham Woodhull, who used the name Samuel Culper. While performing this action, Robert Townsend discovered a shipment of paper that British printers intended to turn into counterfeit bills. After being arrested while performing this action, one man stated “I regret I have but one life to lose for my country.” A “tailor’s apprentice” performs this action in the musical Hamilton. For ten points, name this action performed by Nathan Hale with the goal of reporting British troop movements.",
        "answer": "spying for the United States"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another member of the Culper Ring was this man, a “spy on the inside” according to the musical Hamilton. This New York-based tailor used his slave Cato to smuggle information to George Washington.",
        "answer": "Hercules Mulligan"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Eighty-four pianists performed this piece simultaneously at the opening ceremonies of the 1984 Olympics. Though this piece was orchestrated four times by the composer of the Grand Canyon Suite, Ferde Grofe, its opening was improvised by Ross Gorman. This piece was premiered at a concert, styled “An Experiment in Modern Music,” at Aeolian Hall by Paul Whiteman’s band. A 17-note clarinet glissando open, for ten points, what fusion of jazz and classical forms for piano and orchestra, composed by George Gershwin and given a colorful name?",
        "answer": "Rhapsody in Blue"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The inspiration for Rhapsody in Blue came to Gershwin while he was using this form of travel. A Billy Strayhorn jazz standard popularized by Duke Ellington informs you that, to get to Sugar Hill way up in Harlem, you must use this form of travel.",
        "answer": "train ride"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city hosted the only Olympic performance of Eddie “The Eagle” Edwards, a British ski jumper whose performance was bad enough that the Olympics instituted stricter qualification rules. The first Olympic performance of the Jamaican bobsled team came in this city, whose Olympic Saddledome and Stampede Corral were used as venues for its 1988 Winter Olympics. For ten points, name this Canadian city whose NHL team, the Flames, competes with the Edmonton Oilers for bragging rights in Alberta.",
        "answer": "Calgary"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Canada failed to win an official gold medal in the Calgary Olympics, but did win a gold medal in this demonstration sport, which involves 40-pound stones. Since this sport was re-added to the Olympics in 1998, Canada has never failed to medal.",
        "answer": "Men’s and/or Women’s curling"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Bob Dylan refused to appear on this show when network officials asked him to not play “Talkin’ John Birch Paranoid Blues.” This show displayed the caption “SORRY GIRLS, HE’S MARRIED” on February 9, 1964. Charles Laughton filled in as host of this show on the first night that this show featured Elvis Presley, although this show’s cameramen zoomed in to avoid broadcasting Elvis’s provocative dancing. For ten points, name this CBS show that ran until 1971 and which drew over 70 million viewers for its first broadcast of The Beatles.",
        "answer": "The Ed Sullivan Show"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "For the Beatles’ first appearance, Ed Sullivan noted that a telegraph of support had come in from Elvis and this man, his longtime manager.",
        "answer": [
          "Colonel Tom Parker",
          "Thomas Andrew Parker",
          "Andreas Cornelis van Kujik"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1975, the CIA made estimates on this country’s military efforts by counting the number of baseball diamonds built in Angola. Similarly, in 1970, the presence of a soccer field instead of baseball diamonds on Cazo Alcatraz in this country’s port of Cienfuegos suggested to the CIA that the Soviet Union, not this country, was building naval infrastructure here. For ten points, name this country that hosted a set of Soviet-deployed missiles in 1962, leading to a namesake “crisis.”",
        "answer": "Cuba"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Legend holds that Cuban dictator Fidel Castro once tried out for this MLB team, whose current players include Cuban reliever Aroldis Chapman.",
        "answer": "New York Yankees"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At the beginning of this event, a cannon firing led to the release of 25,000 pigeons, many of whom defecated on the audience. Avery Brundage controversially pulled Marty Glickman and Sam Stoller out of participation in this event, where Louis Zamperini competed in the 5,000 meters and Luz Long competed against an African-American track and field star who won four gold medals. For ten points, name these pre-World War II Olympic games that were overseen by Adolf Hitler.",
        "answer": [
          "1936 Summer Olympics in Berlin",
          "any answer with Olympics and at least two of the other three underlined parts."
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This German filmmaker and Nazi propagandist documented the 1936 Summer Olympics in her 1938 film Olympia.",
        "answer": "Leni Riefenstahl"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this film, a bag of diamonds is given as a bribe to convince a man to redirect a train. Near the end of this film, a ring inscribed “Whoever saves one life, saves the world” is given to the title character. At age 3, Oliwia Dabrowska played a girl in a red coat in this film, whose director refused to take a salary for it. Itzhak Stern assists the protagonist of this film, in which Amon Goth oversees a concentration camp. For ten points, name this Steven Spielberg film about a factory owner who saves over 1,000 Jews during the Holocaust.",
        "answer": "Schindler’s List"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The film Schindler’s List was based on a novel by this Australian author, whose 1972 novel The Chant of Jimmie Blacksmith is a fictionalized story of the 19th century bushranger Jimmy Governor.",
        "answer": "Thomas Keneally"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A number one hit by this band was censored by the Francisco Franco administration for its lyric “You can get married in Gibraltar, near Spain.” Windows were smashed after advertising for a single by this band was accidentally interpreted as anti-Semitic graffiti in 1968; that single included a song that criticizes people who “go carrying pictures of Chairman Mao.” The songs “Revolution” and “The Ballad of John and Yoko” were released by, for ten points, what band from Liverpool led by John Lennon and Paul McCartney?",
        "answer": "The Beatles"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Paul McCartney claimed he didn’t realize that writing the name of this song on shop windows would stir up memories of Nazism. This song, which was released as a single with “Revolution,” was originally written to reassure John’s son Julian to “Take a sad song and make it better.”",
        "answer": "Hey Jude"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Rather than using traditional hymns, Michael Tippett incorporated five of these pieces into his oratorio written in response to Kristallnacht, A Child of Our Time. Williams Arms Fisher published an arrangement of seventy of these songs and adapted the Largo second movement of Dvorak’s ninth symphony into one of these works. The Fisk Jubilee Singers famously recorded many of these works, including “Swing Low, Sweet Chariot.” Instruments like early banjos sometimes accompanied the singers of, for ten points, what kind of religious songs, many of which were written by slaves in the American south?",
        "answer": [
          "African-American spirituals",
          "additional information",
          "sorrow songs"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This black sociologist described spirituals as “sorrow songs” in his 1903 essay collection The Souls of Black Folk, which opens each chapter with a selection of spiritual music.",
        "answer": "William Edward Burghardt W.E.B. Du Bois"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Gaspar Fagel spread pamphlets supporting this event, and new French tariffs on herring imports led directly to its occurrence. This event led to the Age of the Projectors and an Act of Toleration to protect non-conformist Protestants. After this event, the Coronation Oath Act, the Declaration of Right, and a Bill of Rights were passed, which allowed for freedom of speech and free elections for Parliament. James II was deposed in favor of his daughter and her husband in, for ten points, what 1688 British regime change?",
        "answer": "Glorious Revolution"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Regnal numbers required. James's daughter and her husband gave their names to a Virginia college, the second-oldest in the United States. Name both James's daughter and her husband, including their regnal numbers as rulers of the United Kingdom.",
        "answer": "Mary II and William III"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During the 1904 Olympic iteration of one of these events in St. Louis, Cuban mailman Andarín Carvajal [[kar-vah-HAHL]] took a nap after breaking a forty hour fast by eating rotten apples. The Chechen-descended Tsarnaev [[zar-\"NIGH\"-yef]] brothers targeted the 2013 Boston iteration of these sporting events by using homemade bombs. The legendary run of Pheidippides [[fy-DIH-peh-deez]] from a battle site to Athens inspired, for ten points, what long-distance running events?",
        "answer": [
          "Marathons",
          "Olympic marathon",
          "Boston marathon",
          "Battle of Marathon"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The first Africans to compete in the Olympics were Tsawana [[sah-WAH-nah]] tribesmen from what is today this nation who ran in the 1904 Marathon. Other athletes from this nation include golfer Gary Player and disgraced runner Oscar Pistorius.",
        "answer": [
          "Republic of South Africa",
          "RSA"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Rulers of this culture were known as wanax, and this culture is associated with a state known as Ahhiyawa [[ah-hee-YAH-wah]] in Hittite sources. The Lion’s Gate was excavated at the entrance to the namesake city of this culture. It‘s not Troy, but that city of this culture was excavated by Heinrich Schliemann [[SHLEE-mahn]], who publicized a golden death mask he found there. Michael Ventris deciphered the Linear B script used by, for ten points, what Ancient Greek culture of the Late Bronze Age?",
        "answer": "Mycenaeans ] or Mycenae"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "That golden death mask discovered by Schliemann was named for this mythical king of Mycenae, despite there being no evidence that it belonged to him.",
        "answer": [
          "Agamemnon",
          "Mask of Agamemnon"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Most of Beach Boys member Dennis Wilson's possessions were stolen by acolytes of this man. This man predicted the occurrence of a race war between Blacks and whites which he named after a Beatles song. A former lover and follower of this man, \"Squeaky\" Fromme, attempted to assassinate President Gerald Ford in 1975. For ten points, name this cult leader, the head of a namesake \"Family\" who murdered actress Sharon Tate.",
        "answer": [
          "Charles Manson or Charles Milles Manson",
          "or Charles Milles Maddox"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which Beatles song names Charles Manson's term for a race war between Blacks and whites which he predicted would lead to the end of the world?",
        "answer": "\"Helter Skelter\""
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Pliant Mahon [[PLY-ant muh-HAHN]] received a fourteen-year prison sentence during this conflict in which Deputy Bill Dempsey was killed by Frank Phillips. This conflict escalated over the failure of Perry Cline to win a lawsuit regarding a deed of land. Jim Vance may have started this conflict, in which one side’s cabin was burned during the New Year’s Massacre. Figures like Randolph \"Ole Ran'l\" and \"Devil Anse\" took part in, for ten points, what feud between two rural families in West Virginia and Kentucky?",
        "answer": "Hatfield-McCoy Feud"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Both families were involved in the illicit trade of which specific type of bootleg liquor common in the South whose name is derived from it being made at night?",
        "answer": "Moonshine"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Baseball",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "home city of the Negro Leagues’ Monarchs and the 2015 World Series champion Royals.",
          "answer": "Kansas City"
        },
        {
          "question": "team whose “Core Four,” including Mariano Rivera and Derek Jeter, won five World Series.",
          "answer": "New York Yankees"
        },
        {
          "question": "MLB team that signed Jackie Robinson to break the color barrier.",
          "answer": [
            "Brooklyn Dodgers",
            "city",
            "team name"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "St. Louis Cardinal slugger whose 70 home runs in 1998 won a “race” with Sammy Sosa.",
          "answer": "Mark McGwire"
        },
        {
          "question": "event, called the “Midsummer Classic,” where teams ran out of players in 2002, causing a controversial tie game.",
          "answer": "All-Star Game"
        },
        {
          "question": "team once owned by Nazi-sympathizer Marge Schott, which won two World Series with Pete Rose?",
          "answer": [
            "Cincinnati Reds",
            "city",
            "team name"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "controversial event that prematurely ended the 1994 season and canceled the World Series?",
          "answer": "players’ strike"
        },
        {
          "question": "Chicago Cubs executive who ended the “Curse of the Bambino” as Boston’s General Manager in 2004?",
          "answer": [
            "Theo Epstein The Light Has Gone Out The phrase “the light has gone out of my life,”",
            "“of our lives,” has been used momentously twice in"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "surname will only get you prompted. Who...",
      "prompt": "Answer these questions about surname will only get you prompted. Who......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Re-married Aristotle Onassis after the assassination of her husband, John?",
          "answer": [
            "Jacqueline or “Jackie” Bouvier Kennedy Onassis",
            "any",
            "all underlined parts"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Campaigned for Hillary Clinton and campaigned against child obesity over the last eight years?",
          "answer": "Michelle Robinson Obama"
        },
        {
          "question": "Wrote “Remember the ladies” in a letter to her husband, John, in 1776.",
          "answer": "Abigail Smith Adams"
        },
        {
          "question": "Saved a picture of George Washington when the British burned the White House?",
          "answer": "Dolley Payne Madison"
        },
        {
          "question": "Suffered the loss of her son Tad 6 years after her husband was assassinated?",
          "answer": "Mary Todd Lincoln"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pushed for highway beautification in the 1960s?",
          "answer": [
            "Claudia Taylor Johnson",
            "Lady Bird Johnson"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Is known for her support of the temperance movement, even though her husband, Rutherford, actually banned alcohol from the White House?",
          "answer": "”Lemonade” Lucy Webb Hayes"
        },
        {
          "question": "Died shortly after her husband, Andrew Jackson, was elected.",
          "answer": "Rachel Donelson Jackson"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This character was created in 1941 for Pep Comics. He is the namesake of a company that published Super Cops and Mighty Crusaders under the Red Circle imprint, and he often irritates the wealthy Mr. (20 pts)",
        "Lodge. In the 1970s, this character was the leader of a fictional band that sang the song (10 pts)",
        "\"Sugar, Sugar.\" For 10 points, name this red-haired comic book character who hangs out in Riverdale with Jughead, Betty and Veronica."
      ],
      "answer": "Archie Andrews"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s father was an Olympic boxer for Iran, while he himself won the 1996\nOlympic gold medal in men’s singles for tennis. In the early 1990’s, he attracted\ncontroversy for his flamboyant (20 pts) ",
        "dress, but also gained an endorsement deal for Canon\ncameras where he said the tagline, “Image is everything.” He is the most recent American\nto achieve the career (10 pts) ",
        "Grand Slam, and he is married to German legend Steffi Graf. For 10\npoints, name this tennis player and Las Vegas native, who was perhaps the greatest rival to Pete\nSampras."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Andre Agassi",
        "Agassi"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this film, the title character builds a Chicago opera house in an attempt to make his\nsecond wife, Susan Alexander, into a movie star. Jerry Thompson attempts to research the\nlife of this film’s title character, who had built the (20 pts) ",
        "Xanadu estate. This movie begins\nwith its title character dropping a snowglobe after whispering the word (10 pts) ",
        "“Rosebud.” For\n10 points, name this Orson Welles movie about a newspaper magnate."
      ],
      "answer": "Citizen Kane"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man replaced Vin Diesel in the lead role for the sequel XxX: State of the Union. This\nman was attacked by his former bandmates on the EP 100 Miles and Runnin at the same\ntime that he released his solo debut, (20 pts) ",
        "AmeriKKKa's Most Wanted. This star of the (10 pts) ",
        "Barbershop series wrote more lyrics for NWA than any other member. For 10 points, name this\ngangsta rapper turned family comedian, the star of the Are We There Yet? movies."
      ],
      "answer": "Ice Cube"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This band instigated the so-called \"Riverport Riot\" when its lead singer jumped into the crowd to fight with a man taking pictures, then quit the show, causing a serious incident near St. Louis. In 2008, (20 pts)",
        "Dr Pepper attempted to make good on a promise to give every American a free can of soda upon the release of this band's tremendously delayed album (10 pts)",
        "Chinese Democracy. For 10 points, name this 1980s rock band of Use Your Illusion and the song \"November Rain.\""
      ],
      "answer": "Guns n Roses"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This woman had to sell her husband's papers and the Montpelier plantation to secure an income late in life. This woman, who was raised as a Quaker, sold a slave to Daniel Webster. She performed ceremonial functions for (20 pts)",
        "Thomas Jefferson, a widower, while her own husband was (10 pts)",
        "Secretary of State. For 10 points, name this First Lady from 1809 to 1817, who is most known for saving the Lansdowne portrait of George Washington from the burning White House."
      ],
      "answer": "Dolley Madison"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Apart from Morehead State, one team from this state has won the Ohio Valley Conference 23 times. The most successful team from this state has the most wins in college basketball history. Two teams in this state met in the Final Four of the (20 pts)",
        "2012 NCAA Tournament, and the winning team was led by players such as Michael (10 pts)",
        "Kidd-Gilchrist and Anthony Davis. For 10 points, name this state whose two most successful college basketball teams are led by John Calipari and Rick Pitino, who has coached at Louisville since 2001."
      ],
      "answer": "Kentucky"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In his first Olympics, this man faced controversy over claims he threw his qualification race to allow Shani Davis to make the Olympic team. In that same Olympics he was awarded gold after the South Korean winner was disqualified for illegally (20 pts)",
        "blocking him. In 2007, this athlete competed in and won the spring season of (10 pts)",
        "Dancing with the Stars. For 10 points, name this Olympic speed skater, who, with four bronzes, two silvers, and two gold medals, is the most decorated American Winter Olympic athlete of all time."
      ],
      "answer": "Apolo Anton Ohno NHBB B 2014-2015"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man heavily weakened the influence of John Lilburne’s Leveller Faction, against whom he and his son-in-law Henry Ireton argued in the Putney Debates. He rose to power with John Lambert’s Instrument of Government and increased his influence by ordering (20 pts)",
        "Pride’s Purge, which ended the Long Parliament and instituted the Rump Parliament. This man’s victory at the Battle of Preston during a war that saw his service in the (10 pts)",
        "New Model Army under Thomas Fairfax led to the execution of the Stuart king Charles I. For ten points, name this “Lord Protector,” who won the English Civil War."
      ],
      "answer": "Oliver Cromwell"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This musician canceled a tour of the USSR and said Eisenhower had “no guts” in response to the President’s reluctance to intervene on behalf of the Little Rock Nine. According to legend, he dropped his sheet music while recording (20 pts)",
        "“Heebie Jeebies;” his improvised wordless vocals popularized scat singing. This leader of the (10 pts)",
        "Hot Five earned a number one hit at the age of 63 with his cover of “Hello Dolly”. For ten points, name this jazz trumpeter and vocalist, nicknamed “Satchmo,” who also sang “What a Wonderful World.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Louis Armstrong"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The range of notes used in this genre is known as the ambitus. The only surviving alternative to this system is Ambrosian, heard in Milan, and it replaced the Mozarabic system in Spain during the Reconquista. This (20 pts)",
        "monophonic vocal music arose from a synthesis of Roman and Gallican rite during the reign of (10 pts)",
        "Charlemagne. For ten points, name this type of plainchant, the official liturgical music of the Catholic Church, attributed to and named for a sixth-century Pope."
      ],
      "answer": "Gregorian chant"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One report on this event revealed communication between John Jastremski and Jim McNally; that report, a 243-page document written by Ted Wells, was limited by the destruction of a cell phone. A (20 pts)",
        "D’Qwell Jackson interception prompted this scandal, which ended with the forfeiting of a first round draft pick from (10 pts)",
        "Robert Kraft’s team but, ultimately, no suspension for Tom Brady. For ten points, name this 2015 scandal in which the New England Patriots were accused of tampering equipment during the NFL playoffs."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Deflategate",
        "Ballghazi",
        "any description of a scandal in which footballs were deflated"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A former employee of this organization alleged that “company men A and F” wanted to fix a 2002 event in favor of Los Angeles. Bill Kennedy, another employee of this organization, came out as (20 pts)",
        "gay in December 2015 after being the target of a homophobic slur by Rajon Rondo. Former referee (10 pts)",
        "Tim Donaghy gambled on games run by this organization under commissioner David Stern. For ten points, name this professional sports league that may have rigged the 1984 draft lottery to give Patrick Ewing to the New York Knicks."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "National Basketball Association or NBA",
        "National Basketball Referees Association",
        "NBRA",
        "descriptions thereof"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One hymn adopted as an anthem during this conflict was William Billings’ “Chester.” Richard Schuckburg wrote the lyrics for a song, popular during this conflict, that mocked the enemy’s lack of (20 pts)",
        "fashion sense. After the climactic battle of this war, the defeated army supposedly played “The World Turn’d Upside Down.” The winners of this war were mocked by the line “stuck a (10 pts)",
        "feather in his hat and called it macaroni.” “Yankee Doodle” was a popular song during, for ten points, what war that ended with British defeat at Yorktown?"
      ],
      "answer": "American Revolutionary War or equivalents"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The “bells were ringing out” for this event as “the NYPD choir sing[s] ‘Galway Bay’” in The Pogues’ “Fairytale of New York.” Another song about this event asks “And what have you done?” before commanding “Let’s stop all the fight;” that song parenthetically claims (20 pts)",
        "“War is Over” and is sung by John Lennon, Yoko Ono, and a children’s choir. Bob Geldof organized a 1984 single to raise money for an Ethiopian famine; the title of that song asks (10 pts)",
        "“Do They Know It’s” this holiday. For ten points, name this holiday, also the subject of more traditional songs like “Carol of the Bells” and “Santa Claus is Coming to Town.”"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Christmas Day and/or Eve",
        "“Happy Christmas War is Over”",
        "“Do They Know It’s Christmas”, and",
        "it if they finish the lyric, because we’re not really going for the title"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Combatants in this conflict were given Sharps rifles, which quickly became known as “Beecher’s Bibles” due to the crates in which they were delivered. The Lecompton (20 pts)",
        "Constitution failed to resolve this conflict thanks to allegations of voter fraud. During this conflict, the Pottawatomie Massacre was perpetrated by men led by (10 pts)",
        "John Brown. The issue of popular sovereignty helped prompt, for ten points, what 1850s conflict in which pro-slavery “Ruffians” and abolitionist “Free-Staters” battled in the Great Plains?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Bleeding Kansas",
        "close equivalents along the lines of Bloody Kansas"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This musician’s 1956 trip to Ghana and tours for the US State Department inspired an album he made with Dave Brubeck, The Real Ambassadors. This man called President Eisenhower “gutless” for being slow to support the (20 pts)",
        "Little Rock Nine. According to legend, this man dropped his lyric sheet while recording “Heebie Jeebies,” leading to an early instance of scat singing. This leader of the (10 pts)",
        "Hot Five and Hot Seven sang about “trees of green” and “red roses too” in another song. For ten points, name this jazz trumpeter, nicknamed “Satchmo,” who sang “What a Wonderful World.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Louis Armstrong"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One of these events ended after Mike Jones was barely able to stop Kevin Dyson. In the aftermath of one of these events, Trent Dilfer was non-traditionally picked for an ad campaign instead of a man arrested for murder the prior year, (20 pts)",
        "Ray Lewis. Malcolm Butler secured a victory in one of these events by intercepting (10 pts)",
        "Russell Wilson, and in 2017, a 28 to 3 lead was blown, causing Atlanta’s second loss in this event. The Vince Lombardi Trophy is awarded to the winners of, for ten points, what championship game of the National Football League?"
      ],
      "answer": "Super Bowls"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The leader removed from power in this event had campaigned with the slogan “Evolution in Continuity.” Shortly after this event began, a suspension bridge to Almada, colored similarly to the Golden Gate Bridge, was re-named for it. The (20 pts)",
        "beginning of this event was signaled with a Paulo de Carvalho song from the prior year’s Eurovision Song Contest. Marcello (10 pts)",
        "Caetano was removed from power in this event, which ended a regime began by Antonio Salazar. The Estado Novo ended with, for ten points, what peaceful 1974 Portuguese revolution?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Carnation Revolution",
        "25th of April Revolution"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A ray of sunlight hit the casket of Winston Churchill as this song was being performed at his funeral. This song describes a figure who is seen “in the watchfires of a hundred circling camps.” This song, which was first published in the (20 pts)",
        "Atlantic Monthly in 1862, inspired the title of Steinbeck’s The Grapes of Wrath. The music of (10 pts)",
        "“John Brown’s Body” was used for, for ten points, what patriotic song by Julia Ward Howe that begins with the line “Mine eyes have seen the glory of the coming of the Lord”?"
      ],
      "answer": "The Battle Hymn of the Republic"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Until 1924 in Japan, geishas used a variety of this object known as a senko-dokei. In the 1200s, al-Jazari developed one of these devices that relies on a candle. Lewis Mumford traced the medieval development of these objects in a work that argued that these, not (20 pts)",
        "steam engines, were central to the Industrial Revolution. The clepsydra was a type of these devices that relied on the pouring of (10 pts)",
        "water. An 1876 song gave the name “grandfather” to tall standing types of, for ten points, what timekeeping devices?"
      ],
      "answer": "clocks"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The daughters of a figure with this name were killed by Tadodaho. This name, held by a legendary follower of the Great Peacemaker, was commonly used for wampum belts. Edmonia Lewis sculpted a man with this name holding hands with a Dakota (20 pts)",
        "woman and wearing a feathered headdress. In a poem, a man with this name is born to Wenonah and the West Wind by the (10 pts)",
        "shores of Gitche-Gumee and marries Minnehaha. For ten points, give this name shared by a Mohawk founder of the Iroquois Confederacy and a fictional Ojibwe warrior whose Song was written by Henry Wadsworth Longfellow."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Hiawatha",
        "Ayenwatha",
        "The Song of Hiawatha"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) John Singer Sargent painted this figure as portrayed by Ellen Terry, wearing a dress partially made of 1,000 beetle wings and crowning herself. The article “Muddle Instead of Music” in Pravda condemned Dimitri (20 pts)",
        "Shostakovich for an opera titled for this woman of the Mtsensk District. This queen attempts to wash her hands of imagined (10 pts)",
        "blood in the “Out, damned spot” scene of a 1606 play. For ten points, name this treacherous wife who encourages her husband to kill Duncan in Shakespeare’s “Scottish play.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Lady Macbeth"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man starred as Genghis Khan in The Conqueror, a 1956 movie that was filmed downwind of nuclear testing grounds in Nevada; this man died of possibly-related stomach cancer in 1979. This man, who was nominated for an Oscar as a producer on a 1960 film about the (20 pts)",
        "Alamo, won his only Oscar in 1969 for playing Rooster Cogburn in (10 pts)",
        "True Grit. The Shootist, The Searchers, and Stagecoach are among the over 100 films to feature, for ten points, what American western film star?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "John Wayne",
        "Marion Morrison"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this conflict, the pincer movement was utilized in battle for the first time. After a large discovery of silver during this conflict, one side created 200 triremes that fought at Artemisium. One of the early phases of this war was the Ionian (20 pts)",
        "Revolt, and other battles fought during this conflict include the battles of Thermopylae [[ther-MAH-puh-lee]] and (10 pts)",
        "Marathon. For ten points, name this conflict, one side of which was led by men including Darius and Xerxes against a number of smaller city-states centered on the Balkan peninsula."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Greco-Persian Wars",
        "obvious equivalents,",
        "Battle of Marathon before “silver” 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 3"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) HGV driver Stewart Dimmock sued over the distribution of this film. Michael Brook included songs like \"Prof. Revelle\" on this film's soundtrack. The sequel to this film, Truth to Power, was released a year after the signing of the 2016 (20 pts)",
        "Paris Agreement. MIT atmospheric theorist Richard Lindzen criticized this movie as politically biased. Laurie David invited a previous Vice (10 pts)",
        "President to take part in this film, which features ice core data presented in a keynote style. For ten points, name this 2006 film featuring Al Gore on global warming."
      ],
      "answer": "An Inconvenient Truth"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1974, this band took a break from touring to form its own record label, Swan Song, signing artists such as Maggie Bell and Bad Company. Originally known as the New Yardbirds, this band’s first three studio albums were self-titled, and their fourth, untitled album, sometimes referred to as (20 pts)",
        "\"Zoso,\" is one of the best-selling albums of all-time. Many of this band’s songs carry historical and mythological themes, highlighted by the Norse mythology featured in 1970’s (10 pts)",
        "\"Immigrant Song.” For ten points, name this English rock band formed by Robert Plant and Jimmy Page."
      ],
      "answer": "Led Zeppelin"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Born with the surname Gelbfisz, this man formed a partnership with Cecil B. DeMille in 1913 to produce feature-length motion pictures. This man battled Adolph Zukor for control over Paramount Pictures and lost, after which this man created his own film studio under a (20 pts)",
        "new surname. In 1946, the Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences awarded this man the Thalberg Memorial Award for his contributions to the medium of (10 pts)",
        "film. For ten points, name this mogul from the Golden Age of Hollywood whose name contributes a letter to the film studio MGM."
      ],
      "answer": "Samuel Goldwyn"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Shaul Ladany warned people of this event of which \"Issa\" and \"Tony\" were the leaders. The codeword “Sunshine” was supposed to be used during an attack in this event. Andre Spitzer was clubbed in view of cameras during this event. Because of this event, (20 pts)",
        "GSG 9 was created and Ahmed Bouchiki was accidentally killed in Lillehammer, Norway. Israel launched Operation (10 pts)",
        "Wrath of God to target perpetrators of this event which Abu Daoud might have planned for Black September. Occurring at the 1972 Olympics, for ten points, name this massacre of Jewish athletes."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Munich Massacre",
        "Black September Massacre before mentioned",
        "1972 Olympics Massacre before mentioned",
        "\"Kidnapping,\" \"Killing,\" and other words that indicate knowledge of the violence perpetrated in place of Massacre"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A 340-symbol cipher created by this person was deciphered in 2020 by a team including mathematicians and software engineers. Fifty-one years earlier, a 408- symbol cryptogram created by this person was cracked by Donald and Bettye (20 pts)",
        "Harden who determined that it included a reference to “The Most Dangerous Game.” That puzzle was in a collection of letters sent by this person to three (10 pts)",
        "newspapers in 1969, taking credit for a series of California shootings. For ten points, name this still- unidentified serial killer who signed those letters with a crossed circle."
      ],
      "answer": "Zodiac Killer"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "This conscientious objector and trumpeter shot himself in the foot after being enlisted into the Royal Military Band in World War Two. As a composer, this man wrote Concerto for Two Pianos, one of the most often-played works for (*) three hands. From 1947 to 1970, this man wrote the scores for more than 100 films, including Whistle Down the Wind, The Inn of the Sixth Happiness, and (*) Hobson’s Choice. For ten points, name this man who won an Academy Award for the music to David Lean’s The Bridge on the River Kwai."
      ],
      "answer": "Malcolm Arnold"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Chaturanga was an early version of this game, whose early twentieth century champions included Cuban prodigy José Raúl Capablanca. In 2013, World Champion Vishi Anand was defeated by Norwegian (20 pts)",
        "Magnus Carlsen, who claims the highest rating ever in this game. The 1972 World Championship in this game between Boris Spassky and Bobby Fischer (10 pts)",
        "was considered a \"battle\" of the Cold War. For ten points, name this \"Game of Kings\" which boomed in popularity thanks to the Netflix hit The Queen's Gambit."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Chess",
        "Indian Chess",
        "Shogi",
        "Xiangqi before \"Cuban\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This conflict saw the \"Border Ruffians\" engage in electoral fraud, with one of its leaders depicted in the painting \"Tragic Prelude.\" This conflict, derived from popular sovereignty, saw James Buchanan support a \"Lecompton\" constitution. After Charles Sumner was (20 pts)",
        "caned for speaking against this event, radical abolitionists killed five people in the (10 pts)",
        "Pottawatomie Massacre. For ten points, name this conflict during James Buchanan's presidency over whether a Midwestern state would adopt slavery."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Bleeding Kansas",
        "Bloody Kansas",
        "the Kansas Border War 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 10"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Ottoman Empire entered this conflict on the eventual losing side during the Pruth River Campaign. The Treaty of Nystad [[NEE-stad]] allowed the winning side of this war to seize the land to construct a new capital on the Gulf of (20 pts)",
        "Finland. The Battle of Poltava [[pohl-TAH-vuh]] during this conflict ended an invasion of (10 pts)",
        "Russia by King Charles XII [[the twelfth]]. For ten points, name this conflict where Russia under Peter the Great ended the golden age of the Swedish Empire."
      ],
      "answer": "Great Northern War"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Several powers in this conflict were criticized in the pamphlet The Conduct of the Allies. A 70-day siege of Tournai [[toor-NAY]] occurred during this conflict, in which one side lost over 10,000 men in a victory over the Duke of Villars. A monopoly over the (20 pts)",
        "slave trade was given to England in the treaty ending this conflict. A battle in this war led to a number of poems written to celebrate the Duke of (10 pts)",
        "Marlborough. For ten points, name this Europe-wide conflict in which the Battle of Blenheim [[BLEN-em]] was fought."
      ],
      "answer": "War of the Spanish Succession"
    }
  ]
}